<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % tnt SYSTEM "../tnt.ent">
%tnt;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xml:id="language-reference">

<title>Language reference</title>
<blockquote><para>
  This chapter provides a reference of Tarantool data operations
  and administrative commands.
</para></blockquote>
<bridgehead renderas="sect2">Digression: data and administrative ports</bridgehead>
<para>
  Unlike many other key/value servers, Tarantool uses
  different TCP ports and client/server protocols for data
  manipulation and administrative statements.
  On start up, the server can connect to up to five TCP ports:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>
      Read/write data port, to handle INSERTs, UPDATEs,
      DELETEs, SELECTs and CALLs. This port speaks the native
      Tarantool protocol, and provides full access to the server.
      </para>
      <para>
      The default value of the port is <literal>33013</literal>,
      as defined in <olink targetptr="primary_port"/>
      configuration option.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
      Read only port, which only accepts SELECTs, default  port number
      <literal>33014</literal>, as defined in
      <olink targetptr="secondary_port"/> configuration option.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
      Administrative port, which defaults to <literal>33015</literal>,
      and is defined in <olink targetptr="admin_port"/>
      configuration option.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Replication port (see <olink
        targetptr="replication_port"/>), by default set to
        <literal>33016</literal>, used to send updates to
        replicas. Replication is optional, and if this port is not
        set in the option file, the corresponding server process
        is not started.
      </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Memcached port. Optional, read-write data port
      that speaks Memcached text protocol. This port is off by default.
    </para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  In absence of authentication, this approach allows system
  administrators to restrict access to read/write or
  administrative ports. The client, however, has to be aware of
  the separation, and <command>tarantool</command> command line
  client automatically selects the correct port for you
  with help of a simple regular expression. SELECTs, UPDATEs,
  INSERTs, DELETEs and CALLs are sent to the primary port.
  SHOW, RELOAD, SAVE and other statements are sent to the administrative port.
</para>

<section>
  <title>Data manipulation</title>

  <para>Tarantool protocol was designed with focus on asynchronous
    I/O and easy integration with proxies. Each client
    request starts with a 12-byte binary header, containing three
    fields: request type, length, and a numeric id.
  </para>
  <para>
    Five basic request types are supported: INSERT, UPDATE,
    DELETE, SELECT and CALL. The mandatory length, present in the
    header, allows simplifying client or proxy I/O.
    The server response to a request always carries in its header
    the same request type and id.
    The id makes it possible to always match request to a
    response, even if the latter arrived out of order.
  </para>
  <para>Request type defines the format of the payload.
    INSERTs and DELETEs can only be made by the primary key, so
    an index id and key value are always present in these requests.
    SELECTs and UPDATEs can use secondary keys. UPDATE only needs to
    list the fields that are actually changed. With this one
    exception, all commands operate on whole tuple(s).
  </para>
  <para>Unless implementing a client driver, one needn't
    concern him or her self with the complications of the binary
    protocol. <olink targetptr="connectors">Language-specific
    drivers</olink> provide a friendly way to store domain
    language data structures in Tarantool, and the command line
    client supports a subset of the standard SQL.
    A complete description of both, the binary protocol and
    the supported SQL, is maintained in annotated Backus-Naur
    form in the source tree: please see
    <link xlink:href="https://github.com/mailru/tarantool/blob/master/doc/box-protocol.txt"><filename>doc/box-protocol.txt</filename></link>
    and
    <link xlink:href="https://github.com/mailru/tarantool/blob/master/doc/sql.txt"><filename>doc/sql.txt</filename></link> respectively.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Memcached protocol</title>
      <para>If full access to Tarantool functionality is not needed,
      or there is no readily available connector for the
      programming language in use, any existing client driver for
      Memcached will make do as a Tarantool connector.
      To enable text Memcached protocol, turn on
      <olink targetptr="memcached_port"/> in the option file.
      Since Memcached has no notion of spaces or secondary
      indexes, this port only makes it possible to access one
      dedicated space (see <olink
      targetptr="memcached_space"/>) via its primary key.
      Unless tuple expiration is enabled with <olink
      targetptr="memcached_expire"/>, TTL part of the message is
      stored but ignored. Note, that we do not support the binary
      protocol of Memcached. If top performance
      is a must, Tarantool's own binary protocol should be
      used.
  </para>
  </section>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Administrative console</title>
  <para>
    The administrative console uses a simple text protocol.
    All commands are case-insensitive.
    You can connect to the administrative port using any
    <command>telnet</command> client, or a tool like
    <command>rlwrap</command>, if access to readline features is
    desired. Additionally, <command>tarantool</command>, the
    SQL-capable command line client,
    understands all administrative statements
    and automatically directs them to the administrative port.
    The server response to an administrative command, even though
    is always in plain text, can be quite complex.
    It is encoded using YAML markup to simplify automated parsing.
  </para>
  <para>To learn about all supported administrative commands, you
    can type <emphasis role="tntadmin">help</emphasis> in the
    administrative console. A reference description also follows
    below:</para>

  <variablelist>

    <varlistentry>
      <term xml:id="save-snapshot" xreflabel="SAVE SNAPSHOT">
        <emphasis role="tntadmin">save snapshot</emphasis>
      </term>
      <listitem><para>
        Take a snapshot of all data and store it in
        <filename><olink
        targetptr="snap_dir"/>/&lt;latest-lsn&gt;.snap</filename>.
        To take a snapshot, Tarantool forks and quickly
        <function>munmap(2)</function>s all memory except one that
        stores tuples. Since all modern operating systems support
        virtual memory copy-on-write, this effectively creates a
        consistent snapshot of all tuples in the child process,
        which is then written to disk tuple by tuple. Since a
        snapshot is written sequentially, you can expect a very
        high write performance (averaging to 70MB/second on modern
        disks), which means an average database instance gets
        saved in a matter of minutes.  Note, that as long as there
        are any changes to the parent memory through concurrent
        updates, there are going to be page splits, and therefore
        you need to have some extra free memory to run this
        command. 15%-30% of <olink targetptr="slab_alloc_arena"/>
        is, on average, sufficient. This statement waits until a
        snapshot is taken and returns operation result. For
        example:
<programlisting>localhost> show info
---
info:
  version: "1.4.4"
  lsn: 843301
...
localhost> save snapshot
---
ok
...
localhost> save snapshot
---
fail: can't save snapshot, errno 17 (File exists)
...
</programlisting>
      </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>


    <varlistentry>
      <term xml:id="reload-configuration" xreflabel="RELOAD CONFIGURATION">
        <emphasis role="tntadmin">reload configuration</emphasis>
      </term>
      <listitem><para>
        Re-read the configuration file. If the file contains
        changes to dynamic parameters, update the runtime
        settings. If configuration syntax is incorrect, or a
        read-only parameter is changed, produce an error and do
        nothing.
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term xml:id="show-configuration" xreflabel="SHOW CONFIGURATION">
        <emphasis role="tntadmin">show configuration</emphasis>
      </term>
      <listitem><para>
        Show the current settings. Displays all settings,
        including those that have default values and thus are not
        necessarily present in the configuration file.
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term xml:id="show-info" xreflabel="SHOW INFO">
        <emphasis role="tntadmin">show info</emphasis>
      </term>
      <listitem><para>
<programlisting>
localhost> show info
---
info:
  version: "1.4.5-128-ga91962c"
  uptime: 441524
  pid: 12315
  logger_pid: 12316
  lsn: 15481913304
  recovery_lag: 0.000
  recovery_last_update: 1306964594.980
  status: primary
  config: "/usr/local/etc/tarantool.cfg"
</programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">recovery_lag</emphasis> holds the
        difference (in seconds) between the current time on the
        machine (wall clock time) and the time stamp of the last
        applied record.  In replication setup, this difference can
        indicate the delay taking place before a change is
        applied to a replica.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">recovery_last_update</emphasis> is
        the wall clock time of the last change recorded in the
        write ahead log. To convert it to human-readable time,
        you can use <command>date -d@<replaceable>1306964594.980</replaceable></command>.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">status</emphasis> is
        either "primary" or "replica/&lt;hostname&gt;".
      </para>

      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term xml:id="show-stat" xreflabel="SHOW STAT">
        <emphasis role="tntadmin">show stat</emphasis>
      </term>
      <listitem><para>
<programlisting>
localhost> show stat
---
statistics:
  INSERT:        { rps:  139  , total:  48207694    }
  SELECT_LIMIT:  { rps:  0    , total:  0           }
  SELECT:        { rps:  1246 , total:  388322317   }
  UPDATE_FIELDS: { rps:  1874 , total:  743350520   }
  DELETE:        { rps:  147  , total:  48902544    }
</programlisting>
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term xml:id="show-slab" xreflabel="SHOW SLAB">
        <emphasis role="tntadmin">show slab</emphasis>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Show the statistics of the slab allocator. The slab
          allocator is the main allocator used to store tuples.
          This can be used to monitor the total memory use and
          memory fragmentation.
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">items_used</emphasis> contains
          the % of <olink targetptr="slab_alloc_arena"/> already
          used to store tuples.
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">arena_used</emphasis> contains
          the % of <olink targetptr="slab_alloc_arena"/> that is
          already distributed to the slab allocator.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term xml:id="show-palloc" xreflabel="SHOW PALLOC">
        <emphasis role="tntadmin">show palloc</emphasis>
      </term>
      <listitem><para>
        A pool allocator is used for temporary memory, when
        serving client requests. Every fiber has an own
        pool. Shows the current state of pools of all fibers.
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term xml:id="save-coredump" xreflabel="SAVE COREDUMP">
        <emphasis role="tntadmin">SAVE COREDUMP</emphasis>
      </term>
      <listitem><para>
        Fork and dump a core. Since Tarantool stores all tuples
        in memory, it can take some time. Mainly useful for
        debugging.
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term xml:id="show-fiber" xreflabel="SHOW FIBER">
        <emphasis role="tntadmin">show fiber</emphasis>
      </term>
      <listitem><para>
        Show all running fibers, with their stack.
        Mainly useful for debugging.
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term xml:id="lua-command" xreflabel="LUA ...">
        <emphasis role="tntadmin">lua ...</emphasis>
      </term>
      <listitem><para>
        Execute a chunk of Lua code. This can be used to define,
        invoke, debug and drop <olink
        targetptr="stored-programs">stored programs</olink>,
        inspect server environment, perform automated
        administrative tasks.
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>

</section>

<xi:include href="stored-programs.xml" />

</chapter>

<!--
vim: tw=66 syntax=docbk
vim: spell spelllang=en_us
-->
