<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % tnt SYSTEM "../tnt.ent">
%tnt;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xml:id="lua-and-packages">

<title>Lua and the Tarantool Lua Packages</title>

<blockquote>
    <para>
        <link xlink:href="http://www.lua.org">Lua</link>
        is a light-weight, multi-paradigm, embeddable language.
        Stored procedures in Lua can be used to implement
        data manipulation patterns or data structures.
        It is possible to dynamically define, invoke,
        alter and drop Lua functions. Lua functions can run
        in the background and perform administrative tasks.
    </para>
</blockquote>

<para>
<bridgehead renderas="sect4">The "Batteries Included" Lua Software Distribution</bridgehead>
Tarantool incorporates open-source
precompiled packages which Tarantool's developers
have tested for compatibility -- the "built-in" packages.
Tarantool specializes in packages which aid
database applications or which Tarantool's own developers
use to make database-related tools.
At the same time.
Tarantool makes it easy to add new Lua packages
from <link xlink:href=" http://luarocks.org/">LuaRocks</link> -- the "downloadable" packages.
</para>

<para>
The included language processor is <link xlink:href="http://luajit.org/">LuaJIT</link>.
Major "built-in" components are: fibers,
<link xlink:href="http://msgpack.org">MsgPack</link>,
digest, JSON, <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yaml">YAML</link>,
<link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inter-process_communication">IPC</link> , and box.
</para>

<para>
LUAJIT is a processor for the entire Lua language. 
This differs from the original Lua interpreter from
<link xlink:href="http://www.puc-rio.br/index.html">Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio de Janeiro</link>
("RIO-PUC" <link xlink:href="http://www.lua.org/">Lua</link>) 
because the JIT stands for "Just In Time" compiling, that
is, it can compile some Lua code into machine executable form the
after a few executions of the code.
The result is that some
loops will run as quickly as an equivalent C program.
Also some precompiled C code can be brought in using
LuaJIT's FFI (<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign_function_interface">Foreign Function Interface</link>).
Examples for using FFI exist on the Internet, for example 
<link xlink:href="https://github.com/tarantool/tarantool/blob/master/src/box/lua/tuple.lua">tuple.lua</link> on the tarantool.org site.
</para>

<para>
LuaJIT has been compared to competitive implementations
and found to be reliable and efficient,
provided one takes advantage of it where <link xlink:href="http://wiki.luajit.org/Numerical-Computing-Performance-Guide">performance</link> counts. 
</para>

    <para>
        Apart from increased performance, LuaJIT provides such
        features as <link
        xlink:href="http://bitop.luajit.org/">bitwise
        operations</link> and <link xlink:href="#tonumber64">64-bit integer arithmetic.</link>
    </para>

<para>
FIBERS are like Lua coroutines, but as <link xlink:href="http://members.chello.nl/~w.couwenberg/fibers.htm">one fiber developer</link>
put it: "The main difference between a coroutine and a fiber
is that a running fiber can be suspended anywhere in a call
chain, regardless of its C and Lua call stack nesting levels."       
</para>

<para>
MSGPACK is a relatively new way to serialize data.                    
The point of MsgPack is that it can
handle Lua types and C types, with structures and nesting,
without the overhead of an SGML-style markup language.
</para>

<para>
DIGEST is a cryptography package for CRC32, SHA, and MDA.
Nothing new here -- except that Tarantool has made them into a
package, so that one doesn't have to get each one of these
things individually from the <link xlink:href="http://lua-users.org/wiki/CryptographyStuff">many that are available</link>.
And, since Tarantool is binding with FFI rather than a traditional Lua C
API, the routines should run faster on LuaJIT.
</para>

<para>
JSON is a serialization format which has
become popular in the web world. The package within
Tarantool is derived from <link xlink:href="http://www.kyne.com.au/~mark/software/lua-cjson-manual.html">CJSON</link>
which, according to <link xlink:href="http://lua-users.org/wiki/JsonModules">a survey</link>, 
handles Unicode surrogate pairs and is robust when
edge cases come up.
</para>

<para>
YAML is short for "YAML Ain't a Markup Language". YAML is a            
way to show data in human-readable form, without losing
underlying information about typing, arrays, and structures.
</para>

<para>
IPC is Inter-Process Communication.
this is useful for implementations of task queues and long polling.
</para>

<para>
BOX is the NoSQL DBMS that was developed by Tarantool
and its community. Box's architecture and routines will be the
subject of the next chapter.
</para>

<para>
<bridgehead renderas="sect4">The Downloadable Packages</bridgehead>
A directory of Lua Addons packages can be found on the <link xlink:href="http://lua-users.org/wiki/LuaAddons">Lua-users</link> wiki. 
For a "managed package" system equivalent to Perl's CPAN and Ruby's RubyGems and Python's
Eggs, one gets "rocks" (modules or packages) from <emphasis>LuaRocks</emphasis>.
Either way, the installation requirement can be as simple as saying
require('package-name')
and the effect is a simple Lua table containing 
functions and members, superficially like C/Java classes.
</para>

<para>
There are <link xlink:href="https://rocks.moonscript.org/modules">several hundred LuaRocks packages</link> that are not built-in       
but are reasonably easy to obtain by anyone with an Internet
connection. Just as a sampling: ...
<link xlink:href="https://rocks.moonscript.org/modules/kikito/ansicolors">ansicolors</link> for color manipulation,
<link xlink:href="https://rocks.moonscript.org/modules/luarocks/htmlparser">htmlparser</link> for changing HTML text into a tree of elements,
<link xlink:href="https://rocks.moonscript.org/modules/kikito/i18n">i18n</link> an internationalization library,
<link xlink:href="https://rocks.moonscript.org/modules/luarocks/lposix">lposix</link> a POSIX library,
<link xlink:href="https://rocks.moonscript.org/modules/luarocks/lua-spore">lua-Spore</link> a generic ReST client,
<link xlink:href="https://rocks.moonscript.org/modules/luarocks/tekui">TekUI</link> a GUI toolkit.
For example, to bring in the i18n package: install luarocks, say <code>luarocks install i18n</code>,
start Tarantool, and say <code>require('i18n')</code>.
</para>

<para>
The rest of this chapter is an introduction and reference that has what's needed for programming and
administration with the built-in packages.
</para>


<xi:include href="stored-procedures.xml" />
<xi:include href="triggers.xml" />

</chapter>

<!--
vim: tw=66 syntax=docbk
vim: spell spelllang=en_us
-->
