<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % tnt SYSTEM "../tnt.ent">
%tnt;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="data-persistence">
<title>Data persistence</title>
<para>
To maintain data persistence, Tarantool writes each data change
request (INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE, REPLACE) into a write-ahead log (WAL)
file in the <olink targetptr="wal_dir"/> directory.
A new WAL file is created for every <olink
targetptr="rows_per_wal"/> records.  Each data change request
gets assigned a continuously growing 64-bit log sequence number.
The name of the WAL file is based on the log sequence
number of the first record in the file, plus an extension <filename>.xlog</filename>.
</para>

<para>Apart from a log sequence number and the data change request
(its format is the same as in the binary protocol and is described
in <link
xlink:href="http://tarantool.org/docs/box-protocol.html"><filename>docs/box-protocol.html</filename></link>),
each WAL record contains a header, some metadata, and then the data formatted
according to <link xlink:href="https://github.com/msgpack/msgpack/blob/master/spec.md">msgpack rules</link>.
For example this is what the WAL file looks like after the first INSERT
request ("s:insert({1})") for the introductory sandbox exercise
<olink
targetptr="getting-started-start-stop"><quote>Starting Tarantool and making your first database</quote></olink>.
On the left are the hexadecimal bytes that one would see with
<programlisting><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>hexdump 00000000000000000001.xlog</userinput></programlisting>
and on the right are comments.
<programlisting>
Hex dump of WAL file       Comment
--------------------       -------
58 4c 4f 47 0a             File header: "XLOG\n"
30 2e 31 32 0a 0a          File header: "0.12\n\n" = version
...                        (not shown = inserted tuples for LSN and system spaces)
d5 ba 0b ab                Magic row marker always = 0xab0bbad5 if version 0.12
19 00                      Length, not including length of header, = 25 bytes
ce 16 a4 38 6f             Record header: previous crc32, current crc32,
a7 cc 73 7f 00 00 66 39
84                         msgpack code meaning "Map of 4 elements" follows
00 02 02 01                the 4 elements, including 0x02 which is IPROTO_INSERT
03 04 04                   additional information
cb 41 d4 e2 2f 62 fd d5 d4 msgpack code meaning "Double" follows, for next 8 bytes
82                         msgpack code meaning "map of 2 elements" follows
10                         IPROTO_SPACE_ID which is #defined as 16 (hex 10)
cd                         msgpack code meaning 2-digit number follows
02 00                      the id of "tester" which is 513, it's biggest byte first
21                         Flags = IPROTO_TUPLE which is #defined as hex 21
91                         msgpack code meaning "1-element fixed array" follows
01                         Tuple: field[1] value = 1
</programlisting>
</para>

<para>
Tarantool processes requests atomically: a change is either
accepted and recorded in the WAL, or discarded completely.
Let's clarify how this happens, using the REPLACE request as an
example:
<orderedlist>
    <listitem><para>
    The server attempts to locate the original tuple by
    primary key. If found, a reference to the tuple is retained
    for later use.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    The new tuple is then <emphasis>validated</emphasis>. If
    for example it does not contain an indexed field,
    or it has an indexed field whose type does not
    match the type according to the index definition,
    the change is aborted.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    The new tuple replaces the old tuple in all
    existing indexes.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    A message is sent to WAL writer running in a
    separate thread, requesting that the change be recorded in the WAL.
    The server switches to work on the next request until the write 
    is acknowledged.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    On success, a confirmation is sent to the client. Upon
    failure, a rollback procedure is begun.  During the rollback
    procedure, the transaction processor rolls back all changes to
    the database which occurred after the first failed change, from
    latest to oldest, up to the first failed change. All rolled back
    requests are aborted with <olink targetptr="ER_WAL_IO"/>
    error. No new change is applied while rollback is in progress.
    When the rollback procedure is finished, the server restarts
    the processing pipeline.
    </para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>

<para>
One advantage of the described algorithm is that complete request
pipelining is achieved, even for requests on the same value of the
primary key. As a result, database performance doesn't degrade
even if all requests touch upon the same key in the same space.
</para>

<para>
The transaction processor thread communicates with the WAL writer thread
using asynchronous (yet reliable) messaging; the transaction
processor thread, not being blocked on WAL tasks, continues to
handle requests quickly even at high volumes of disk I/O. A
response to a request is sent as soon as it is ready, even if
there were earlier incomplete requests on the same connection. In
particular, SELECT performance, even for SELECTs running on a
connection packed with UPDATEs and DELETEs, remains unaffected by
disk load.
</para>

<para>
The WAL writer employs a number of durability modes, as defined
in configuration variable <olink targetptr="wal_mode"/>. It is
possible to turn the write-ahead log completely off, by setting
<olink targetptr="wal_mode"/> to <emphasis>none</emphasis>.
Even without the write-ahead log it's still possible to take a
persistent copy of the entire data set with the
<olink targetptr="box.snapshot"/> statement.
</para>


</section>
<!--
vim: tw=66 syntax=docbk
vim: spell spelllang=en_us
-->
