<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % tnt SYSTEM "../tnt.ent">
%tnt;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<title>Data persistence</title>
<para>
To maintain data persistence, Tarantool writes each data change
request (INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE) into a write ahead log. WAL
files have extension <filename>.xlog</filename> and are stored in <olink
targetptr="wal_dir"/>. A new WAL file is created for every <olink
targetptr="rows_per_wal"/> records.  Each INSERT, UPDATE or DELETE
gets assigned a continuously growing 64-bit log sequence number. The name of the log file is based on the log sequence
number of the first record this file contains.
</para>

<para>Apart from a log sequence number and the data change request
(its format is the same as in the binary protocol and is described
in <link
xlink:href="https://github.com/mailru/tarantool/blob/master/doc/box-protocol.txt"><filename>doc/box-protocol.txt</filename></link>),
each WAL record contains a checksum and a UNIX time stamp.
</para>

<para>
Tarantool proceeds requests atomically: a change is either
accepted and recorded in the WAL, or is rejected wholesale.
Let's clarify how this happens, using REPLACE command as an
example:
<orderedlist>
    <listitem><para>
    The server tries to locate an old tuple identified by
    the same primary key. If found, the tuple is remembered for
    later.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    The new tuple is <emphasis>validated</emphasis>. If it
    violates any of the unique key constraints, misses
    any of indexed fields, or an indexed field type does not
    match index type, the change is aborted.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    The new tuple is marked 'invisible' and is added to 
    the primary and secondary indexes.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    A message is sent to a separate <quote>wal_writer</quote>
    thread requesting that the change is recorded in the WAL.
    The fiber associate with the current connection is scheduled
    off CPU until an acknowledgment is received from the WAL
    writer.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    Upon success, 'invisible' flag is cleared
    and the old tuple is deleted. A response is sent to the
    client. Upon failure, the new tuple is removed and <olink
    targetptr="ER_WAL_IO"/> error is sent to the client.
    </para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>

<para>
Communication between master and WAL writer threads is asynchronous.
It is implemented using an asynchronous FIFO queue.
Asynchronous but reliable message passing between the master
and WAL writer threads allows Tarantool to continue handling
requests regardless of disk throughput. SELECT performance,
provided SELECTs are run in their own connections, is unaffected
by disk load.
</para>

<para>
WAL writer employs a number of modes for synchronization between
requesting fibers, WAL writer and disk hardware, as defined
in configuration for <olink targetptr="wal_mode"/>.
</para>


</section>
<!--
vim: tw=66 syntax=docbk
vim: spell spelllang=en_us
-->
