<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % tnt SYSTEM "../tnt.ent">
%tnt;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<title>Data persistence</title>
<para>
To maintain data persistence, Tarantool writes each data change
request (INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE) into a write-ahead log. WAL
files have extension <filename>.xlog</filename> and are stored in <olink
targetptr="wal_dir"/>. A new WAL file is created for every <olink
targetptr="rows_per_wal"/> records.  Each INSERT, UPDATE or DELETE
gets assigned a continuously growing 64-bit log sequence number. The name of the log file is based on the log sequence
number of the first record this file contains.
</para>

<para>Apart from a log sequence number and the data change request
(its format is the same as in the binary protocol and is described
in <link
xlink:href="https://github.com/mailru/tarantool/blob/master/doc/box-protocol.txt"><filename>doc/box-protocol.txt</filename></link>),
each WAL record contains a checksum and a UNIX time stamp.
</para>

<para>
Tarantool processes requests atomically: a change is either
accepted and recorded in the WAL, or discarded completely.
Let's clarify how this happens, using REPLACE command as an
example:
<orderedlist>
    <listitem><para>
    The server attempts to locate the original tuple by
    primary key. If found, a reference to the tuple is retained
    for later use.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    The new tuple is then <emphasis>validated</emphasis>. If it
    violates a unique-key constraint, misses
    an indexed field, or an index-field type does not
    match the type of the index, the change is aborted.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    The new tuple is marked 'invisible' and is added to
    the primary and secondary indexes.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    A message is sent to <quote>wal_writer</quote>, running in a
    separate thread, requesting that the change be recorded in the WAL.
    The fiber associated with the current connection is suspended
    until an acknowledgment from the WAL writer.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    Upon success, the 'invisible' flag is cleared
    and the original tuple is deleted. A response is sent to the
    client. Upon failure, the new tuple is removed and <olink
    targetptr="ER_WAL_IO"/> error is sent to the client.
    </para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>

<para>
The master and the WAL writer threads communicate using asynchronous (yet reliable)
messaging; the master thread, not being blocked on
WAL tasks, continues to handle requests quickly
even at hight volumes of disk I/O. For instance, SELECT performance,
provided SELECTs are run in their own connections, remains
unaffected by disk load.
</para>

<para>
WAL writer employs a number of modes for synchronization between
requesting fibers, WAL writer and disk hardware, as defined
in configuration for <olink targetptr="wal_mode"/>.
</para>


</section>
<!--
vim: tw=66 syntax=docbk
vim: spell spelllang=en_us
-->
