<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<title>Preface</title>
<section xml:id="intro">
  <title>Tarantool/Box: an overview</title>
  <para>
    Tarantool/Box, or simply Tarantool, is a high performance
    key/value storage server.  The code is available for free under
    the terms of <citetitle
    xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/license-list.html#ModifiedBSD">BSD
    license</citetitle>. Supported platforms are GNU/Linux and
    FreeBSD.

  </para>

  <para>
    The server <emphasis role="strong">maintains all its data in
    random-access memory</emphasis>, and therefore can handle read
    requests blazingly fast.  At the same time, a copy of the data
    is kept on non-volatile storage (a disk drive), and inserts
    and updates are performed atomically.
  </para>

  <para>
    To ensure atomicity, consistency and crash-safety of the
    persistent copy, a write-ahead
    log (WAL) is maintained, and each change is recorded
    in the WAL before it is considered complete.
  </para>

  <para>
    If update and delete rate is high, a constantly growing
    write-ahead log file (or files) can pose a disk space problem,
    and significantly increase time necessary to restart from disk.
    A simple solution is employed: the server <emphasis
    role="strong">can be requested to save a concise
    snapshot</emphasis> of
    its current data. The underlying operating system's
    <quote>copy-on-write</quote> feature is employed to take the
    snapshot in a quick, resource-savvy and non-blocking manner.
    The <quote>copy-on-write</quote> technique guarantees that
    snapshotting has minimal impact on server performance.
  </para>

  <para>
    Tarantool supports replication. Replicas may run locally or
    on a remote host. Tarantool replication
    is asynchronous and does not block writes to the
    master. When or if the master becomes unavailable, the replica
    can be switched to assume the role of the master.
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Tarantool is lock-free</emphasis>.
    Instead of the underlying operating system's concurrency
    primitives, Tarantool uses cooperative multitasking environment
    to simultaneously operate on thousands of connections. While
    this approach limits server scalability to a single CPU core, in
    practice it removes competition for the memory bus and sets the
    scalability limit to the top of memory and network throughput.
    CPU utilization of a typical highly-loaded Tarantool server is
    under 10%.
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">The software is production-ready</emphasis>.
    Tarantool has been developed and is actively used at
    <citetitle xlink:href="http://api.mail.ru">Mail.Ru</citetitle>
    one of the leading Russian web content providers. At Mail.Ru,
    the sowtware serves the <quote>hottest</quote>
    data, such as online users and their sessions, online application
    properties, the map between users and their serving shards.
  </para>

  <para>
    To conclude, Tarantool/Box is ideal for highly volatile and/or
    highly accessed Web data. With Tarantool, performance overhead
    on serving data is minimal: a single server can easily deal with
    tens or even hundreds of thousands of requests per second.
    Snapshots can be made when Web user activity is at its lowest,
    for example at night, and thus add little or no restraint on the
    top throughput of the system.  If the master becomes
    unavailable, a replica can assume the role of the master with
    minimal downtime.
  </para>
</section>
<section>
  <title>Conventions</title>
  <para>
    This manual is written in <citetitle
    xlink:href="http://www.docbook.org/tdg5/en/html/docbook.html">DocBook
    5</citetitle> XML markup language and is using the standard <citetitle
    xlink:href="http://docbook.sourceforge.net/release/xsl/current/doc/">DocbBook
    XSL</citetitle> formatting conventions:
  </para>
  <para>
    UNIX shell command input is prefixed with '$ ' and is 
    formatted using a fixed-width font:
    <programlisting>
      <prompt>$ </prompt>tarantool_box <option>--daemonize</option>
    </programlisting>
  </para>
  <para>
    The same formatting style is used for file names:
    <filename>/path/to/var/dir</filename>.
  </para>

  <para>
    Text that represents user input is formatted in boldface:
    <programlisting>
      <prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>your input here</userinput>
    </programlisting>

  </para>

  <para>
    Within user input, replaceables are printed in italics:
    <programlisting>
      <prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>tarantool_box <replaceable>--option</replaceable></userinput>
    </programlisting>

  </para>
</section>

</chapter>
<!--
vim: tw=66
vim: spell spelllang=en
-->
