<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % tnt SYSTEM "../tnt.ent">
%tnt;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="replication">

<title>Replication</title>
<blockquote><para>
  To set up replication, it's necessary to prepare the master,
  configure a replica, and establish procedures for recovery from
  a degraded state.
</para></blockquote>

<section>
  <title>Setting up the master</title>
  <para>
    To prepare the master for connections from replica, it's only
    necessary to enable <olink targetptr="replication_port"/> in
    the configuration file. An example configuration file can be
    found in <link
    xlink:href="https://github.com/mailru/tarantool/blob/master/test/box_replication/tarantool.cfg"><filename>test/box_replication/tarantool.cfg</filename></link>. A master with enabled replication_port can accept connections
    from as many replicas as necessary on that port. Each replica
    has its own replication state.
  </para>
</section>
<section>
  <title>Setting up a replica</title>
  <para>
    Replica gets all updates from the master by simply shipping
    the write ahead log (WAL) and applying it.
    Each record in the WAL has a log sequence number
    (LSN), operation type (INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE) and a
    timestamp.
  </para>
  <para>
    For replication to work correctly, the latest LSN
    on the replica must match or fall behind the latest LSN
    on the master. If the replica has its own updates,
    this leads to it getting out of sync since
    updates from the master having identical LSNs are
    not applied. Indeed, if replication is on, Tarantool
    does not accept updates, even on its <olink
    targetptr="primary_port"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
    To "seed" a new replica, it's only necessary to
    configure its <olink targetptr="replication_source_port"/>
    and <olink targetptr="replication_source_ipaddr"/>.
    These configuration parameters are "dynamic", which allows a
    replica to become a master and vice versa with help of
    <olink targetptr="reload-configuration"/> statement.
    The replica uses these configuration parameters to
    connect to the master, and request all changes that
    happened after the latest local LSN. It is therefore
    necessary to keep WAL files on the master host as long as
    there are replicas that haven't applied them yet.
    An example configuration can be found in <link
    xlink:href="https://github.com/mailru/tarantool/blob/master/test/box_replication/tarantool_slave.cfg"><filename>test/box_replication/tarantool_slave.cfg</filename></link>.
  </para>
  <para>
    In absence of WALs, a replica can be "seeded" at any time
    with a snapshot file, manually copied from the master.
  </para>

</section>
<section>
  <title>Recovering from a degraded state</title>
  <para>
    "Degraded state" is a situation when the master becomes
    unavailable -- either due to hardware or network failure, or a
    programming bug. There is no reliable way for a replica to detect
    that the master is gone for all, since sources of failure and
    replication environments vary significantly.
  </para>
  <para>
    A separate monitoring script (or scripts, if decision making
    quorum is desirable) is necessary to detect a master failure.
    Such script would typically try to update a tuple in an
    auxiliary namespace on the master, and raise alarm if a
    network or disk error persists longer than is acceptable.
  </para>
  <para>
    When a master failure is detected, the following needs
    to be done:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          First and foremost, make sure that the master does not
          accepts updates. This is necessary to prevent the
          situation when, should the master failure end up being
          transient, some updates still go to the master, while
          others already end up on the replica.
        </para>
        <para>
          If the master is available, the easiest way to turn
          on read-only mode is to turn Tarantool into a replica of
          itself. This can be done by setting master's <olink
          targetptr="replication_source_ipaddr"/> and <olink
          targetptr="replication_source_port"/> to point to self.
        </para>
        <para>
          If the master is not available, best bet is to log into
          the machine and kill the server, or change the
          machine's network configuration (DNS, IP address).
        </para>
        <para>
          If the machine is not available, it's perhaps prudent
          to power it off.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Record the replica's LSN, by issuing <olink
          targetptr="show-info"/>. This LSN may prove useful if
          there are updates on the master that never reached
          the replica.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Propagate the replica to become a master. This is done
          by setting <olink targetptr="replication_source_port"/>
          on replica to <constant>0</constant>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Change the application configuration to point to the new
          master. This can be done either by changing the
          application's internal routing table, or by setting up
          old master's IP address on the new master's machine, or
          using some other approach.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Recover the old master. If there are updates that didn't
          make it to the new master, they have to be applied
          manually.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
</section>

</chapter>

<!--
vim: tw=66 syntax=docbk
vim: spell spelllang=en_us
-->
