<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % tnt SYSTEM "../tnt.ent">
%tnt;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xml:id="triggers">
  <title>Defining triggers in Lua</title>
<blockquote>
    <para>
    Triggers are Lua scripts which are executed by the server
    when certain events happen. Currently the two types of
    triggers are <link linkend="on_replace">on_replace</link> triggers
    which for database events, and connection triggers,
    which are executed when a new connection
    is created or dropped.
    Triggers must be set up when the server starts.
    This is most commonly done in <olink
    targetptr="init.lua">the initialization script</olink>.
    The performance
    overhead of triggers, as long as they are not defined, is
    minimal: merely a pointer dereference and check. If a
    trigger is defined, its overhead is equivalent to the
    overhead of calling a stored procedure.
    </para>
</blockquote>
<section xml:id="sp-box-session-triggers" xreflabel="session triggers">
    <title>Connection triggers</title>
<variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
        <term>
            <emphasis role="lua">box.session.on_connect(chunk) </emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem><para>
	      	Set a callback (trigger) for invoking on each connected session.
        The callback doesn't get any arguments, but is the first
        thing invoked in the scope of the newly created session.
        If the trigger fails by raising an error, the error
        is sent to the client and the connection is shut down.
        Returns the old value of the trigger.
        </para>
        <warning>
        <para>
        If a trigger always results in an error, it may become
        impossible to connect to the server to reset it.
        </para>
        </warning>
        </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
        <term>
            <emphasis role="lua">box.session.on_disconnect(chunk)</emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem><simpara>Set a trigger invoked after a client has
        disconnected. Returns the old value of the trigger. If
        the trigger raises an error, the error is logged but otherwise
        is ignored. The trigger is invoked while the session associated
        with the client still exists and can access session properties,
        such as id.
        </simpara></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

</section>

<!--
vim: tw=66 syntax=docbk
vim: spell spelllang=en_us
-->
